Wickham family papers MSS 15753
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
- Correspondence of the Wickham and related families
  - Personal Correspondence of Littleton Waller Tazewell (1774-1860) with William F. Wickham, 1817-1849; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 14)
    Topics include the perils of travel by stage to Norfolk, Virginia, in winter (March 3, 1817); condolence letter upon the death of his friend, John Wickham, and reflections upon Wickham's importance in his own life as a mentor and friend and his singular character (January 26, 1839); the mention of Tazewell in the will of John Wickham (March 17 and April 1, 1839); ten inch snowfall in March and the economic difficulties of the country (March 21, 1843); discussion on the political issue on "our title to Oregon" (February 26, 1846); and Tazewell thanking William F. Wickham for his translations of Italian comedies, but does not think they merit the efforts of someone of Wickham's ability in the Italian language (July 15, 1849).
  - Personal Correspondence of Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 1818, 1835-1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include: William B. Bowers; E.E. Cooke; E.S. Holmes; E. Laurens; Robert E. Lee; L.M. Mason; N.W. Massie; Catharine H. Myers; [J.] R. Ritchie; E.R. Simons; Sue R. Simons; and Sallie P. Winston. The letter from Robert E. Lee to his cousin, Anne B. Carter Wickham, November 11, 1862, hand-written copy, expresses his regret that her son, Williams Carter Wickham, has again been wounded but explains that he cannot spare Wickham from returning to duty in the army.
    The original of the Lee letter has been transferred to the Robert E. Lee papers.
  - Personal correspondence of Henry Taylor Wickham concerning the death of his father, Williams C. Wickham, arranged alphabetically by the name of correspondent, 1888; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Among the numerous correspondents are George Washington Custis Lee; Mildred Lee; W.H.F. Lee; General William Mahone; Francis H. Smith; and George D. Wise.
  - Personal Correspondence of Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913), 1865-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence of Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) to Bessie (Elizabeth) Kane Shields, 1844-1847; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1842-1863; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 5)
    The original of letters to Robert E. Lee have been transferred to the Robert E. Lee papers, the originals of the letters from Henry Clay transferred to the Henry Clay papers and those from John Singleton Mosby were transferred to the John Singleton Mosby papers.
    Correspondents include: John Minor discussing the two engravings, of General Marion and "the Artist's Dream," sent by the Apollo Association for the Promotion of the Fine Arts in the United States and the current relations of the United States and England, especially as affected by the affair of the Creole (March 18 and October 12, 1842); Henry Clay declines an invitation to visit (February 22, 1848); John S. Mosby, concerning the service of the late Dr. James McClurg as a surgeon in the Revolutionary War (July 16 and August 6, 1849); Francis Robert Rives (1822-1891); Andrew Stevenson (1784-1857) concerning politics and slavery (February 15, 1850) and a visit (July 20, 1854); John R. Thompson, editor of the Messenger, refusing an essay by Wickham defending the Mormons (December 4, 1850); Edward Vernon Childe (1804-1861) writes concerning the peace negotiations during the Crimean War (December 18, 1855); and two drafts of a letter from Wickham to Robert E. Lee concerning the arrival of the Yankee cavalry at "Hickory Hill," who carried off General W.H. F. Lee as a prisoner in Wickham's carriage as well as horses and slaves, and includes the report that Charlotte Lee's health is not good and that she is much distressed at her husband's capture (June 28, 1863).
  - Personal Correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1870-1880; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Topics include financial inquiry about Virginia's non-payment of the interest on state stock (January 17, 1872); the fire at Hickory Hill, Hanover County, Virginia (February 15, 1875); the voyage of William D. Shipman to England and his assessment of Thomas Jefferson's life and career (July 4, 1876); Wickham's analysis of State Trials of the United States by Francis Wharton, including his own memories of the James T. Callendar trial (June 19, 1876); and William D. Shipman's mention of seeing the effigy of ancestor William of Wykeham in Winchester, England and information about him (November 6, 1876).
  - Personal Correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) with Conway Robinson (1805-1884), 1860-1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    Topics include advice for Henry T. Wickham on entering the legal profession and the study of law (July 24, 1868); Robinson's work with a case in the Supreme Court concerning Allen T. Caperton (1810-1876) and his acts in West Virginia as Provost Marshal (April 15, 1872).
  - Personal Correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham, 1836, 1861-1864; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Topics include the declaration of [William B.] Preston for the immediate secession of Virginia from the Union and Wickham's fear that "the dogs of war will be let loose" (April 16, 1861); two letters from Colonel [Beverly Holcombe] Robertson about missing and absent soldiers and his efforts to round them up (May 13 and 14, 1862); request for Wickham's support and vote for Robert H. Wynne as doorkeeper of the Confederate House of Representatives (December 24, 1863); John B. Baldwin informs Williams Carter Wickham that his nomination has not been acted upon (February 5, 1864) and two letters from John Taylor about family and home events during the Civil War (February 2 and 8, 1864).
  - Personal Correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham, 1865-1885; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    The originals of Lee letters were transferred to Robert E. Lee papers.
    Topics include a letter from Robert E. Lee about Henry T. Wickham's attendance at Washington College in Lexington and Lee's plan to write a history about military campaigns in Virginia during the Civil War (October 3, 1865) and a draft of Wickham's reply to Lee in the hand of Lucy Wickham [October 13, 1865]; a draft of Wickham's letter to General W.H.F. Lee about contemporary politics (April 16, 1868); the formation of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad (September 17, 1868); Horace Greeley's comments on the progress of the railroads in Virginia (November 15, 1868); request and recommendation from Alexander H.H. Stuart on behalf of two job seekers in the railroad business (May 5, 1873); efforts of C.T. Smith to get Wickham elected (August 19, 1883); two congratulatory letters on the recent election of Wickham to the Virginia Senate from B. Johnson Barbour and John T. Harris (November 19, 1883); and a request for a donation towards a University of Virginia chapel from Schele de Vere (November 21, 1883).
  - Personal correspondence of Eunice Lynn Wingfield, consisting of condolence letters upon the death of her husband, Henry Brown Wingfield., 1938; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Financial Papers, Legal Papers, and Miscellany
  - Commonplace book of Julia L. Wickham, after 1845; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Diary from Hickory Hill, kept presumably by Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), 1860-1861; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 2)
    The diary begins with an entry about the secession of South Carolina from the Union and continues with entries about the evacuation of Fort Moultrie and the removal of troops to Fort Sumter in South Carolina; each state that secedes from the Union is noted and mention made of the firing upon the steamer Star of the West at Charleston, South Carolina; Intermixed with news of the impending war are notes about building a henhouse, nests, the receipt of toys, and weather; his father [Williams Carter Wickham] as a candidate for the Virginia Secession Convention from Henrico (January 29, 1861); and ends with an entry for February 12, 1861.
  - Diary, incomplete with loose pages, probably kept by [Captain George Annesley Barksdale (1835-1910)], 1861 May-October; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 3)
    The diary mentions the following topics: the loan of a sharps rifle from George W. Randolph, supposedly owned before by John Brown and presented to the 1st [Virginia?] Regiment at Harper's Ferry; a four mile drive on the Petersburg Road to "Strawberry Hill" owned by Robert Edmond; Judge and Mrs. Robertson leaving for "Mount Athos" their place in the country near Lynchburg, Virginia; double guard on "the mills" [Gallego Mills?]; the arrival of 1,000 men from Tennessee who went to the old fairgrounds; a drill by the "Richland Rifles" at the South Carolina camp; occupation of Alexandria by President Lincoln's troops; news of a battle at Bethel Church between Yorktown and Hampton; the departure of 2,000 troops for Manassas on June 13th; a visit to Camp Lee; examination of the fortifications below the city with locations noted; note that business is very slow since the commencement of the war; the meeting with Mr. and Mrs. Macfarland and General Lee at Mr. Lyon's [home?]; birth of a daughter [Elise Warwick Barksdale Wickham (1861-1952)] on August 28, 1861; note that he spent the last month with the 16th Virginia Regiment as Quartermaster at "Camp Withers" six miles from Norfolk; his orders to transfer to Colonel L. Smith's office as paymaster, September 13, 1861; and the death of cousin Fanny Townes, September 20, 1861.
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1704-1792; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1800-1817; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Subjects include: lists of books purchased from Peter Cotton (October 20, 1816-January 27, 1817 and September 22, 1817); purchases of quills, paper, ink, chessmen, etc. (October 15, 1817); slave hires (January 25 and 27, 1817 and February 21, 1817); and a bill of sale for slaves (September 17, 1817).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1818-1820; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Subjects include: medical care for slaves from Dr. W.P. Jones (January 12, February 24 and 26, March 24, and June 24, 1818); slave hire (April 2, 1819); and a bill of sale for two male slaves (January 19, 1820).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1821; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Subjects include: the return of a little boy, Joe Lewis, and little girl, Lucy, the property of William F. Wickham (September 28, 1821); payment to overseer William Lizer on "South Wales" plantation (January 26, 1821); and purchase of paper, ink, and books (July 7, 1821).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1822-1829; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 8)
    Subjects include: hire of a slave girl, Jenny (January 11, 1823).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1830-1840; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 9)
    Subjects include: hiring of Nathaniel B. Priddy as overseer (1834-1835; 1837-1838, 1840); and a list of books and magazines, quills, pencils, and paper purchased (1836-1838).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1841-1844; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Subjects include: hiring of Samuel Bumpass as overseer (1842); sale of slave boy, Washington (January 6, 1843); hiring of Nathaniel B. Priddy as overseer (1843); sale of Nancy Wylde and her two youngest children (May 23, 1843); and sale of Ned Davis (June 27, 1843).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1845-1847; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 11)
    Subjects include: lists of books and writing supplies purchased (July 20, 1846; March 22 and April 16, 1847).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1848-1849; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: lists of books and writing supplies purchased (February 1848; July 14, 1848; and October 4, 1849).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1850-1851; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Subjects include: lists of books purchased (January and November 1850); memoranda book containing names of slaves (May 12, 1850); and slave hires of Giles, Frank, and John from J.H. Wickham (1851).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1852-1856; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Subjects include: list of taxable property for William F. Wickham in 1853, includes 96 slaves over 16 years old, 116 slaves over twelve years old.
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1857-1860; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Subjects include: partners listed for Warwick and Barksdale at the "Gallego Mills" following the death of William J. Barksdale (February 15 and July 2, 1860).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1861-1869; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Subjects include: theft of stock certificates, bank book, and checks from Williams Carter at the "North Wales" plantation during a Yankee raid (May 31, 1864); copy of the last will and testament of Williams Carter with a codicil dated July 30, 1864, freeing his two slaves, Margaret and Sally with any offspring that they have as soon as peace shall be established in the country (July 17, 1864); mulatto girl named Sally lent to Anne Butler Berkeley by Williams Carter (August 10, 1864); indenture concerning the former plantations and property of Williams Carter, Sr. including "North Wales" and "Broad Neck" (May 16, 1867); and payroll lists (April 1, 1868).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1870-1874; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 6)
    Subjects include: receipts for work in the coal banks, Clifton, West Virginia (1873).
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1875-1876; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1877-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Financial and Legal Papers, 1880-1946; 1 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Financial and Legal Papers, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: a valuation of personal property at "North Wales" plantation; valuation of real estate of Mr. [Abraham] Warwick made by commissioners, including factories, blacksmith shop, houses, lots, and a Brookfield farm; and a list of slave names with values.
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Checks on the National Bank of Virginia, 3 folders, 1866-1878; 3 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 2-4)
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Deeds and indentures, 1768, 1817, 1822; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box M-35, Oversizefolder 3)
    These three oversize items include an indenture between Betty Littlepage and Charles Carter of Corotoman (May 5, 1768); a deed of trust from Carter B. Page and Rebecca Page to Thomas Taylor and Benjamin Harrison (June 17, 1817); and an indenture concerning Catherine Page, "Broad Neck" and Williams Carter (March 11, 1822).
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Deeds, indentures, and a bill of sale, 1735-1820; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box S-69, Oversizefolder 4)
    The oversize deeds and indentures include those signed by Carter B. and Rebecca Page and Thomas Taylor (June 7, 1817); an indenture between John Wickham, Edward Carrington, Daniel Call, and Littleton Waller Tazewell (March 17, 1800); an indenture between Harry and Anna Terrell and Charles Carter (October 7, 1769); an indenture between James Littlepage and Joel Terrell (April 23, 1751); an indenture between John Littlepage and John Carter (March 2, 1735); and a bill of sale for two male slaves, Billy and Cyrus (January 15, 1820).
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Dr. Charles Carter, 1867-1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Lists of slaves, 1835-1865; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 6)
    These include a list with the heading "A List of My Slaves, such as I wish to keep, such as I may wish to sell and may wish to send to the West" with names, ages, special skills or jobs, and their values on the "Rocky Mills" and "South Wales" plantations belonging to Edmund Fanning Wickham in 1835; an account of sale of land and slaves at "Rocky Mills" in November 1842 with the name of the purchaser, name of the slave and the prices; list of slaves treated by Dr. J.P. Harrison (April 24, 1844; July 1845; July 1848); list of William F. Wickham's slaves by age category (1843); value of Tom Christian and his entire family (December 22, 1846); list of named slaves with their ages belonging to the estate of Dr. James McClurg, Hanover County, Virginia, valued by W. O. Winston (January 18, 1852); list of 209 named slaves belonging to [William F. Wickham?] (January 1854); list of 269 named slaves belonging to [William F. Wickham?] (January 1859); list of slaves belonging to [William F. Wickham?] who were either carried off the plantation by Yankee forces or left of their own accord during the Civil War (1862-1864); and one list of male slaves between the ages of 18 and 55 with the notation that two are in Confederate service, 14 remain on the plantation and 33 are gone to the enemy (January 31, 1865) and another list of slaves that went to the enemy by year, 120 in all [1865].
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Miscellany, 1784, 1835, 1840; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box S-69, Oversizefolder 5)
    These six oversize items include four land grant certificates to Edmund F. Wickham and Edwin P. Crenshaw; a London Medical Society membership certificate for Dr. James Maclurg (1784); a letter from Lucy Nelson (1835).
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Plats, 1779-1858, undated; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box M-35, Oversizefolder 2)
    The oversize plats include one for "North Wales" plantation belonging to Charles Carter, October 4, 1779; a plat of "South Wales" and Lane plantations, Hanover County, according to the division of January 1818, but updated on May 21, 1858; a plat showing the part of "South Wales" plantation allotted to Anne B. Carter, the purchase of land by W.F. Wickham from Thomas Carter, and "Hickory Hill" plantation purchased by W.F. Wickham from the estate of George W. Smith, November 27, 1825; plat of "Verdon" Hanover County, Virginia, belonging to the estate of John T. Anderson (December 1, 1865); and an undated plat showing parcels of land west of the Missouri River, apparently belonging to Thomas Gorham and a Wickham family member, 4 items.
  - Financial and Legal Papers – Plats and Surveys, 1818, 1837-1842; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box S-69, Oversizefolder 6)
    These six oversize items include a survey of the Broad Neck or Big Neck tract for Thomas C. Nelson (September 8, 1818); survey of the Lane tract, part of the South Wales Estate (January 1818); plat of the Lane tract, South Wales and Hickory Hill (January 1818); fields laid off and numbered from a survey of W.F. Wickham's river fields (February 16, 1837); surveys no. 137 and no. 146 in Saline County, Missouri for Edmund F. Wickham (1841); diagram of land plots to the west of the Missouri River and the 5th principal meridian, presumably in Missouri [1841-1842?].
  - Genealogy and history of the Wickham family, 1799-1985, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 1)
    This material includes a recollection of George Wythe by William F. Wickham (1874); and the first recollection of General Robert E. Lee by Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly, written in a letter to her brother Henry (undated); biographical sketches of Captain William C. Wickham, U.S. Navy (April 19, 1962 and September 1985), John Wickham (undated), and General Williams Carter Wickham (undated); and history of "Hickory Hill" (undated).
  - Genealogy and family history of related families, 1874, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Families discussed include Fanning, Leiper, Martian, Peyton, Pye, Tabb and Barksdale, Taylor, Warwick, and Wingfield.
  - Genealogical - Carter family tree, [1878 July]; 1 folder(s) (Oversize folder flat file 267, Oversizefolder 1)
  - Genealogical chart section for the Neale descendants of Thomas Wickham, born about 1624, undated; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box M-35, Oversizefolder 3)
  - Hair of John Graham Wickham (1855-1860), Julia L. Wickham (1859-1873) and presumably Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), 1860-1888; 3 items (Oversize box AB-30, Object D)
  - Invitations and calling cards, 1875-1950, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Military papers of General Williams Carter Wickham and Captain Williams Carter Wickham, U.S. Navy, 1861-1864, 1944; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 4)
    This includes a report of [3rd (Wickham's) Virginia Cavalry Brigade] near Front Royal, Virginia (August 23, 1864).
  - Miscellany, 1857-1949, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 5)
    This folder includes such items as the weather at Hickory Hill (1857); a prayer of Bishop Meade (1861); printed advertisement for a catalog of attorneys (1875); damaged circular from a Rochester nursery (1882); a horse pedigree (undated); and "Notes on Planting Box at Williamsburg" by Arthur A. Shurcliff (undated).
  - News clippings, chiefly Henry T. Wickham, 1906-1936, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Manuscripts of William F. Wickham, 1876, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 7)
    These include Wickham's notes concerning the "Home Reminiscences of John Randolph, of Roanoke" by Powhatan Bouldin, the benefits of lime and marl, and W.W. Mac Farland's address.
  - Photographs, 1869-1949; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 8)
    These include [Julia L. Wickham], "Peliso" Orange, Virginia, gardens in Rome, [Hickory Hill], and Captain Williams C. Wickham, U.S. Navy.
  - Poetry, 1856, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Recipes, 1855, 1868, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - School papers, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Sympathy and greeting cards, 1917-1959; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 12)